Sylvanus Cadwallader Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Sylvanus Cadwallader Papers 1818-1904 (bulk 1862-1898)
MSS14712
Cadwallader, Sylvanus, b. 1825 or 6
250 items 1 container .4 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist and public official. Correspondence, writings, and newspaper articles, and other papers relating primarily to Cadwallader’s activities as a journalist reporting on the operations of the Union Army and Ulysses S. Grant during the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Babcock, Orville Elias, 1835-1884--Correspondence.; Badeau, Adam, 1831-1895--Correspondence.; Bennett, James Gordon, 1795-1872--Correspondence.; Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821--Correspondence.; Bower, Theodore S.--Correspondence.; Brady, John A.; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1795-1858--Correspondence.; Cadwalader family.; Cadwallader, Mary Isabella Paul.; Cadwallader, Sylvanus, 1825 or 1826-; Carson, Samuel Price, 1798-1838--Correspondence.; Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917--Correspondence.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852--Correspondence.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892--Correspondence.; Dana, Charles A. (Charles Anderson), 1819-1897--Correspondence.; Dent, Frederick T. (Frederick Tracy), 1820-1892--Correspondence.; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879--Correspondence.; Grant, Frederick Dent, 1850-1912--Correspondence.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885--Correspondence.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Hudson, Frederic, 1819-1875--Correspondence.; Macon, Nathaniel, 1757-1837--Correspondence.; McCullagh, Joseph B. (Joseph Burbridge), 1842-1896--Correspondence.; Meade, George Gordon, 1815-1872--Correspondence.; Paul family.; Pendleton, George H. (George Hunt), 1825-1889--Correspondence.; Porter, Horace, 1837-1921--Correspondence.; Rawlins, John A. (John Aaron), 1831-1869.; Richie, Thomas--Correspondence.; Roane, Spencer, 1762-1822--Correspondence.; Rublee, Horace, 1829-1896--Correspondence.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869--Correspondence.; Townsend, George Alfred, 1841-1914--Correspondence.; Wilson, James Harrison, 1837-1925--Correspondence.
Subjects
Freemasonry.; Journalism--United States.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Journalists.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Wisconsin--Officials and employees.
Occupations
Journalists.; Public officials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Sylvanus Cadwallader, journalist and public official, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1965.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Sylvanus Cadwallader are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Sylvanus Cadwallader, born in Ohio in 1825 or 1826, attended school in Ross County, Ohio, and moved to Kenosha, Wisconsin, in the early 1850s, where he started a newspaper career before becoming co-publisher with his brother-in-law, George H. Paul, of the Milwaukee Daily News. As a journalist with Union forces after 1861, he wrote for the Chicago Times and reported on General Ulysses S. Grant’s advance on Richmond for the New York Herald, including the surrender in April 1865 of General Robert E. Lee at Appomattox Court House. Reportedly an assistant secretary of state of Wisconsin after the war, 1874-1878, he later moved to Missouri and then to San Diego, California. His account of his war experience, Three Years with Grant, as Reported by War Correspondent Sylvanus Cadwallader, written in California in 1876, was first published in 1955 (New York, Alfred A. Knopf), edited and with an introduction and notes by Benjamin P. Thomas.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Sylvanus Cadwallader (born 1825 or 1826) consist primarily of correspondence and telegrams spanning the years 1818-1904, with the bulk of the material dating between 1862-1898. The correspondence is supplemented by newspaper clippings, military passes, printed material, invitations, and commissions.
Cadwallader, as a journalist during the Civil War years, was closely associated with General Ulysses S. Grant and his staff. He was with Grant during the Mississippi and Tennessee operations as a correspondent of the Chicago Times, and later, during the advance on Richmond, Cadwallader accompanied Grant as a representative of the New York Herald. He was present at the surrender of General Robert E. Lee at Appomattox Court House on April 9, 1865. A contemporary drawing of the McLean house made by Cadwallader is in the collection. Credited with being one of the most capable of the wartime correspondents, Cadwallader received a letter from Grant on September 23, 1864, congratulating him for his journalistic ability and his factual reporting.
After the war Cadwallader became a state official in Wisconsin, later moved to Missouri, and finally removed to California where he wrote of his wartime experiences. His reminiscences were edited by Benjamin P. Thomas and published under the title Three Years with Grant.
There are two types of correspondence in the collection, family and general. The family correspondence, spans the years 1849-1897, with the bulk of the letters dated in the 1860s. Included are letters to his wife, Mary Isabella Paul Cadwallader, his daughter, and close personal friends. General correspondence dates from 1862 to 1904, but relates principally to the 1880s and 1890s. Correspondents in this group include Orville Elias Babcock, Adam Badeau, Elias Boudinot, Theodore S. Bower, Benjamin F. Butler, William E. Chandler, Frederic T. Dent, William Lloyd Garrison, Frederick Dent Grant, Ulysses S. Grant, George Gordon Meade, George H. Pendleton, Horace Porter, Edwin McMasters Stanton, William T. Sherman, and James Harrison Wilson. Still other correspondents are newsman such as James Gordon Bennett, George William Curtis, Charles A. Dana, Frederic Hudson, Joseph B. McCullagh, Horace Rublee, and George Alfred Townsend.
Letters and telegrams from the Civil War period primarily concern Cadwallader's newspaper activities, his travels as a war correspondent, and the death of his daughter in Wisconsin. There is also a file of telegrams for the period September-October 1864, relating to Cadwallader's attempt to secure a substitute and thereby prevent being drafted into the army.
Letters from 1880s and 1890s concern the career of General John A. Rawlins, General Grant's major aide-de-camp, and the whereabouts of his personal papers. Most of these letters are from James Harrison Wilson.
Also in the collection are files on Cadwallader's masonic activities, 1849-1890; stock certificates, 1865-1867; appointments to office in Wisconsin 1859-1863; military passes 1862-1865; and invitations, cards, and newspaper clippings.
Papers that may have been collected by Cadwallader include an 1833 letter from Nathaniel Macon to Samuel Price Carson and two letters from Spencer Roane, one to Henry Clay, 1820, the other to Thomas Richie, undated.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm79014712
Container List
- Appointments, 1859-1883 (Box 1)
- Appomattox Courthouse, Va., sketch and description, 1865-1866 (Box 1)
- Brody, John, portrait, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Family, 1849-1897 (Box 1)
  - General, 1862-1904, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Telegrams, 1865-1866 (Box 1)
- Draft notice and substitute certificate, 1864 (Box 1)
- Free masons, 1849-1890 (Box 1)
- Grant, Ulysses S., 1863-1864, undated (Box 1)
- Invitations, 1864-1868, undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia, 1818-1833, undated (Box 1)
- Military passes, 1862-1865 (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Cadwallader, Isabella, circa 1850-1870 (Box 1)
  - Cadwallader, Sylvanus, 1886-1897 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1856-1899 (Box 1)
- New York Herald, undated (Box 1)
- Printed matter, 1870-1874 (Box 1)
- Stock certificates, 1865-1877 (Box 1)